United World Federalists mss. IV, 1927-2011 LMC 2807
Lilly Library
United World Federalists mss. IV
1927-2011
Lilly Library
United World Federalists
LMC 2807
2 Boxes
The United World Federalists mss. IV, 1927-2011, consists of books, pamphlets, and research related to the United Nations, the environment, and generalized politics, as well as copies of World Federalist Association annual reports, the World Federalist News magazine, and miscellaneous related awards and conferences materials.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2011
Biographical Note
The World Federalist Association is a non-partisan, non-profit organization with members in forty-eight states. It has 350 chapters in thirty-nine states, a chapter in Hawaii and state-wide branches in twenty-seven states. The primary purpose of the organization is: (1) to achieve permanent peace through universal disarmament enforced by law; (2) to release for the satisfaction of human needs the resources that at present must be used in continuous preparation for war; (3) to maintain and promote human freedom, and to mobilize support for free institutions among all peoples; (4) to secure to all peoples the right to develop according to their own customs and traditions. Based entirely in the United States it is one of the largest member organizations of the World Federalist Movement. While the two organizations work closely together on many programs they are incorporated separately, with separate staffs, headquarters, and governing boards.
Scope and Content Note
The United Nations series includes books and pamphlets relating to the United Nations, especially regarding reform. General Politics includes books and pamphlets discussing politics between the years of 1927-2011. The Environmental series includes books and pamphlets regarding environmental issues. World Federalist Association Annual Reports includes annual reports from the WFA from the years 1987-1995. The World Federalist News Magazine series includes copies of the WF Magazine from Autumn 1989. Awards and Conferences includes materials related to The Johnson Foundation conference and The Stanley Foundation awards.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into the following series: I. United Nations, II. General Politics, III. Environmental, IV. World Federalist Association Annual Reports, V. World Federalist News Magazine, VI. Awards and Conferences.
Related Material
See United World Federalists mss. I, United World Federalists mss. II, United World Federalists mss. III, and United World Federalists mss. V, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
International relations; United States—Politics and government—20th century; Environmental policy; United World Federalists; United Nations
- I. United Nations
  - Handbook of Proposals for UN Reform; 2001, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Additional UN Options to Combat International Terrorism; Hoffmann, Walter and Randolph, David; 2002 (Box 1)
  - Elements of UN Reform; n.d. (Box 1)
  - President Carter's Report on the Reform and Restructuring of the United Nations System; 1978 (Box 1)
  - A New World Order; 1991 (Box 1)
  - Defining Purpose: The UN and the Health of Nations; 1993 (Box 1)
  - Rethinking Basic Assumptions about the United Nations; 1992 (Box 1)
  - Proposal for A General UN System for Protection of the Environment…; n.d. (Box 1)
  - International Peacekeeping: History and Strengthening; 1989 (Box 1)
  - The Law of the Sea; 1989 (Box 1)
  - A more secure world: Our Shared Responsibility; 2004 (Box 1)
  - The United Nations in its Second Half-Century; 1995 (Box 1)
  - The Case for a United Nations Parliamentary Assembly; Heinrich, Dieter; 1992 (Box 1)
  - An Agenda for Peace; Boutros-Ghali, Boutros; 1992 (Box 1)
  - A Reader on Second Assembly and Parliamentary Proposals; Mendlovitz, Saul H and Walker, Barbara; 2003 (Box 1)
  - The Great Debate on Charter Reform; Logue, John; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Parallel United Nations Charter Hearings; 1974 (Box 1)
  - Bridging the Commitment – Capacity Gap; Langille, H. Peter; 2002 (Box 1)
  - E-democracy and the United Nations; Panganiban, Rik; 2004 (Box 1)
  - Brochure: Center for UN Reform Education (Box 1)
  - Letter to President; 1971 (Box 1)
- II. General Politics
  - The Global Citizen; Spring 2011 (Box 1)
  - Structures for Peace Convocation; Stewart, James R.; 1989 (Box 1)
  - Disputes Processing Research Program, Series 7; Bilder, Richard B.; 1986 (Box 1)
  - The Hard Road to World Order; Gardner, Richard N.; 1974 (Box 1)
  - The Responsibility to Protect: Report of the International Commission on Intervention and State Sovereignty; 2001 (Box 1)
  - A Common Sense Guide to World Peace; Ferencz, Benjamin B.; 1985 (Box 1)
  - The International History Review, Volume VII Number 4; 1985 (Box 1)
  - The Interdependence of Nations; Brown, Lester R.; 1972 (Box 1)
  - The Stockholm Initiative on Global Security and Governance; 1991 (Box 1)
  - The Control of Chemical and Biological Weapons; 1971 (Box 1)
  - Building an International Criminal Court for the 21st Century; MacPherson, Bryan F.; 1998 (Box 1)
  - World Order: The Need for a Bold New Approach; Clark, Grenville; 1961 (Box 1)
  - Toward Understanding Global Governance; Ku, Charlotte and Weiss, Thomas G.; 1998 (Box 1)
  - Grenville Clark, World Federalist; Baratta, Joseph Preston; 1985 (Box 1)
  - Congressional Record; December 1971 (Box 1)
  - Senate Hearing; 1927 (Box 1)
- III. Environmental
  - The Crucial Decade: The 1990s and The Global Environmental Challenge; 1989 (Box 2)
  - Effective Global Environmental Protection; Leonard, Pamela; 1990 (Box 2)
  - Environment and Development; 1992 (Box 2)
  - International Environment: International Agreements are Not Well Monitored; 1992 (Box 2)
  - Breathing Easier: Taking Action on Climate Change, Air Pollution, and Energy Insecurity; MacKenzie, James. J.; n.d. (Box 2)
  - The Ozone Layer; 1987 (Box 2)
  - Partnership for the Planet: An Environmental Agenda for the United Nations; French, Hilary F.; 1995 (Box 2)
  - Costly Tradeoffs: Reconciling Trade and the Environment; French, Hilary F.; 1993 (Box 2)
  - A Nuclear Waste Primer; 1980 (Box 2)
  - Climatic Crisis: A World Federalist Response; 1989 (Box 2)
  - Environment: The First Decade 1972-1982; United Nations Environment Programme (Box 2)
  - Environmental Problems: A Global Security Threat; The Stanley Foundation; 1989 (Box 2)
  - The Fate of the Oceans; Logue, John J.; 1972 (Box 2)
- IV. World Federalist Association Annual Reports
  - 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - 1991 (Box 2)
  - 1995 (Box 2)
- V. World Federalist News Magazine
  - Autumn, 1989 (Box 2)
- VI. Awards and Conferences
  - The Johnson Foundation; Wingspread Conference; 1992 (Box 2)
  - The 1967 Grenville Clark Editorial Page Award; The Stanley Foundation (Box 2)